<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>m.m.r</title>
    <description>Monumental Movement</description>
    <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://monumental-movement.jp/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 20:31:30 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 20:31:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.4.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 コルラ・パンディットとエキゾチカの幻影：ポスト戦後アメリカの夢と仮面</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue-what-was-exotica&quot;&gt;Prologue: What was exotica?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: mmr｜Theme: Exploring the role of Korla Pandit in the nascent period of exotica and the aesthetics of Orientalism in postwar American culture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/4d/Korlaorgan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Korla Pandit at the organ&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korla_Pandit&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Korla Pandit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America in the 1950s.
A music called &lt;strong&gt;Exotica&lt;/strong&gt; appeared at a time when television was common in homes and the Cold War and prosperity coexisted.
It was a sonic expression of Orientalism, depicting “foreign countries” such as the South Pacific, Asia, and Africa as imaginary paradises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiki culture, Hawaiian bars, rumba rhythms, and exotic melodies.
In the center was the mysterious keyboard player “Korla Pandit”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/uChjf1Zmqkw?si=2mU2mDJa1V1Esw63” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;table of contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 1: The mysterious man named Korla Pandit] (#Chapter 1)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 2: Postwar America and “Foreign Dreams”] (#Chapter 2)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 3: The Birth of Exotica Music - From Les Baxter to Martin Denny] (#Chapter 3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 4: Idols of the TV Age - The Shock of “Korla Pandit Show”] (#Chapter 4)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 5: The Truth Behind the Mask - Confessions of John Rowland] (#Chapter 5)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 6: Reverberations of Exotica - From Longines Symphonette to Lo-Fi Revival] (#Chapter 6)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chapter 7: Modern Reappraisal and Cultural Dislocation] (#Chapter 7)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Chronology: Korla Pandit and the History of Exotica Music (1940–2020)] (#Chronology)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Charts&quot;&gt;Charts and Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Conclusion: Between fiction and truth] (#Conclusion)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-a-mysterious-man-named-korla-pandit-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: A mysterious man named Korla Pandit {#Chapter 1}&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1948, Korla Pandit was the “Prince of India” who appeared on Los Angeles television station KTLA.
He wears a turban, looks deep into the camera, and plays the Hammond organ.His fingers danced smoothly across the keys, and he didn’t say a word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the late 1990s, shocking facts were revealed in the documentary film Korla (2014).
His real name was &lt;strong&gt;John Roland Redd&lt;/strong&gt;, and he was African American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “story of the mask” goes beyond a simple stage name anecdote.
&lt;strong&gt;It brings to light the triple structure of race, foreign countries, and art in postwar American society&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-postwar-america-and-foreign-dreams-chapter-2&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Postwar America and “foreign dreams” {#Chapter 2}&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In America in the early 1950s, in the shadow of victory in World War II and the Cold War,
``A yearning for the unknown’’ = &lt;strong&gt;Exoticism&lt;/strong&gt; has become a cultural boom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;``South Pacific’’ (1958) was a big hit in Hollywood.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tiki bars became popular in homes, and bamboo furniture and tropical-patterned curtains filled the dreams of the common man.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In terms of music, Latin, Hawaiian, Arabian, and Indian music were consumed as “fantasy background music.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, the Pandit’s silence and mask came to symbolize an idealized “foreign tranquility.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-the-birth-of-exotica-music---from-les-baxter-to-martin-denny-chapter-3&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: The Birth of Exotica Music - From Les Baxter to Martin Denny {#Chapter 3}&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
timeline
title Genealogy of exotica music
1940 : Les Baxter&apos;s &quot;Ritual of the Savage&quot; appears
1957 : Martin Denny “Exotica” hit
1958 : Arthur Lyman &quot;Taboo&quot;
1961 : Yma Sumac “Legend of the Sun Virgin”
1990 : Re-evaluation by Combustible Edison
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les Baxter’s 1952 album “Ritual of the Savage”
It laid the foundation for the later sounds of Martin Denny and Arthur Lyman.
There, percussion instruments, bird calls, gamelan, and chimes intermingled to create an acoustic version of the ``imaginary South Seas.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pandits, on the other hand, focus more on religious and spiritual aspects,
He pioneered a unique path of ``meditative and euphoric organ music.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference/Source:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Baxter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Les Baxter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Denny&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Martin Denny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-idols-of-the-television-age---impact-of-korla-pandit-show-chapter-4&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: Idols of the Television Age - Impact of “Korla Pandit Show” {#Chapter 4}&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ul_glviDp2M?si=duNBy74VCRrDdxPI” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Korla Pandit Show, which aired from 1951, was one of the first American music television shows.
The production, which was constructed using only sight and sound without uttering words, provided a ``safe foreign country’’ for white viewers at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pundit has had more than 1,000 broadcasts, giving her more television exposure than her contemporaneous Nat King Cole.
However, the fact that he was only able to succeed by hiding his identity as a black artist;
It is also a symbolic anecdote that illustrates the relationship between entertainment and racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-the-truth-behind-the-mask---confessions-of-john-rowland-chapter-5&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: The Truth Behind the Mask - Confessions of John Rowland {#Chapter 5}&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1998, according to an article published by Los Angeles Magazine,
Pandit’s true identity is revealed to be &lt;strong&gt;John Roland Redd&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was born in St. Louis, Missouri in 1916 and became an accomplished pianist in his teens.
While working at a radio station in the 1940s, he created the fictional setting of an ``Indian prince.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than being a “black musician” in a discriminatory era,
I can be accepted as a “foreign aristocrat”.
It was a strategic disguise for a painful reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-reverberations-of-exotica---from-longines-symphonette-to-lo-fi-revival-chapter-6&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: Reverberations of Exotica - From Longines Symphonette to Lo-Fi Revival {#Chapter 6}&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 1970s, exotica was once forgotten.
However, in the 1990s, a re-evaluation began with the &lt;strong&gt;Lounge revival movement&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combustible Edison&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Esquivel reissue CD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sampling by DJ Shadow and Beck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These waves of reappraisal also belatedly shed light on Pandit.
Since the 2000s, his videos and records have been rediscovered as collector’s items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;Chronology&quot;&gt;Chronology: Korla Pandit and Exotic Music History (1940–2020)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Events&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1916&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;John Roland Redd (later Korla Pandit) is born&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1948&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Starts appearing on TV, using the name “Korla Pandit” on KTLA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1951&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Korla Pandit Show” begins broadcasting&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1957&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Martin Denny’s “Exotica” tops the charts&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1960&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The height of the exotica boom in America&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1970&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fewer TV appearances, performing in Las Vegas and other places&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True identity revealed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Movie “Korla” released&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;His recordings are reissued and archived&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;Chart&quot;&gt;Chart: Diffusion of exotica culture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph TD
A[Hollywood movie] --&amp;gt; B[Exotica music]
B --&amp;gt; C[Tiki culture]
C --&amp;gt; D[Lifestyle consumption]
B --&amp;gt; E [Modern Lo-Fi Sound]
E --&amp;gt; F[Chillout / Vaporwave]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;Conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Between fiction and truth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Korla Pandit’s life was at the intersection of artistic creation and social constraints.
His silence may have been the most eloquent protest of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sounds of exotica are not just “tropical BGM”.
&lt;strong&gt;It was a fantasy device to fill the void in the hearts of post-war Americans&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind the mask that symbolizes that fantasy, there was the pain and dream of a black pianist.
We can finally find out now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;referencesource&quot;&gt;Reference/Source&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korla_Pandit&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Korla Pandit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exotica_(music)&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Exotica (music)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Baxter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Les Baxter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Denny&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Martin Denny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-korla-pandit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-korla-pandit/</guid>
        
        <category>Exotica</category>
        
        <category>History</category>
        
        <category>Lounge</category>
        
        <category>70s</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 Vijaya Anandと『Dance Raja Dance』 — カーニバルとしての南インド映画音楽</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue-the-beat-revolution-of-south-india-in-the-late-1980s&quot;&gt;Prologue: The beat revolution of South India in the late 1980s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Text: mmr&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Theme: At the end of the 1980s, urban culture in southern India exploded with disco.Vijaya Anand’s ‘Dance Raja Dance’ is about the sound and visual carnival of Karnataka.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980s, the Indian film industry was in the midst of change.Mumbai’s Hindi cinema (Bollywood) was at a turning point before A.R. Rehman, and a new sound was needed.Meanwhile, in the Kannada film industry (Sandalwood), &lt;strong&gt;Vijaya Anand&lt;/strong&gt; was experimenting with pioneering musical innovations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released in 1987, Dance Raja Dance was more than just an entertaining film.It was the intersection of South Indian sensibilities and global disco culture, and was the “sound of the future” for young people in regional cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-the-phenomenon-of-vijaya-anand&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: The phenomenon of Vijaya Anand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/FC0E48KzEws?si=t5KiwiyVndEMDRAA” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anand (real name: S. V. Krishna Reddy) started his career as a film music composer in the early 1980s.Although he was under the influence of &lt;strong&gt;Ilaiyaraaja&lt;/strong&gt;, who was an overwhelming presence at the time, he stood out in that he aimed for a more &lt;strong&gt;urban/electronic sound&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characteristics of his music can be summarized in the following three points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Western Disco&lt;/strong&gt; — Synth bassline inspired by the rhythmic structure of Giorgio Moroder and Van McCoy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fusion with traditional Indian scales&lt;/strong&gt; — Reconstructing Karnataka music raga on 4/4 beat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration with cinematic production&lt;/strong&gt; — The music was not just an insert song, but functioned as the ``engine’’ of the production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``Dance Raja Dance’’ is the most sophisticated crystallization of these elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-the-incident-called-dance-raja-dance-1987&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: The incident called “Dance Raja Dance” (1987)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/ecf7DWHrOCw?si=u8czeUUGR57RIcSi” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film was the culmination of a &lt;strong&gt;musical-action-romance&lt;/strong&gt; that brought together the stars of the time: director D. Rajendra Babu, lead actor Vishnuvardhan, and actress Khushbu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;story-summary&quot;&gt;Story summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young man named Raja (Vishnuvardhan) lives as a dancer in a downtown area, but gains national popularity after participating in a television dance contest.After going through betrayal, love, and family secrets, they finally express their ``own roots’’ through dance, a moving story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot is simple, but what is noteworthy is the integration of the production and music.The title song ``Dance Raja Dance’’ is said to be the first song in Indian film history to combine electronic drums and Kannada rap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-disco-phenomenon-in-india-in-the-1980s&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: “Disco” phenomenon in India in the 1980s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the success of &lt;code&gt;Disco Dancer&apos;&apos; (1982, Hindi) and&lt;/code&gt;Ilamai Oonjal Aadukirathu’’ (1978, Tamil), disco culture spread throughout India as a symbol of ``dance = freedom.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In South India, this trend took on a unique variation.While Mumbai’s discotheques depicted an &lt;code&gt;urban dream&apos;&apos;, **discotheques in Kannada films were an expression of&lt;/code&gt;regional pride’‘**.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anand’s music bridges rural and urban rhythms by fusing electronics with folk percussion instruments (thaviru, dhol, nadaswaram).
This “hybridity” is the core of South Indian music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-video-production-and-dance-choreography&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: Video production and dance choreography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dance scenes in ``Dance Raja Dance’’ were so ingenious that they exceeded the limits of Indian film technology at the time.Making full use of lighting, smoke, and mirror effects, a &lt;strong&gt;video art composition&lt;/strong&gt; that looks like it’s aimed at the MTV generation is developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choreographer was Mugur Sundar (later the father of famous dance master Prabhu Deva), who was up-and-coming at the time.
While he referenced steps from Hollywood movies, he boldly mixed in elements of &lt;strong&gt;Bharatanatyam hand gestures (mudras)&lt;/strong&gt; and folk dance.
This “South Indian MTV feel” was later inherited by A.R. Rehman and Harris Jayaraj.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-changes-in-social-background-and-audience-demographics&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: Changes in social background and audience demographics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980s, southern India was undergoing a period of expansion of television culture, along with a wave of urbanization.
It was a time when the state-run broadcaster Doordarshan opened up to commercial broadcasting, and young people from rural areas dreamed of becoming stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting in which the main character of &lt;code&gt;Dance Raja Dance&apos;&apos;, Raja, becomes famous through a TV show truly symbolizes the germination of neoliberal values.
Overcoming the constraints of work, class, and family and achieving success through talent and hard work—this can be called the&lt;/code&gt;Indian version of the American Dream.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-soundtrack-analysis&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: Soundtrack Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Song title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Singer&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Features&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dance Raja Dance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;S.P. Balasubrahmanyam&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Electronic drum + folk rhythm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Opening theme&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prema Prema&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;S. Janaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Synth pad + raga melody&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Romantic scene&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ninna Preetige&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mano, Vani Jairam&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Call and Response Structure&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Used in Contest Situations&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finale Medley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Various&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reprise composition of all songs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dance final scene&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been confirmed that these songs were created using cutting-edge equipment at the time, such as FM synth (Yamaha DX7) and Roland TR-707.
In particular, the &lt;strong&gt;rising brass synth sound&lt;/strong&gt; heard in the intro of ``Dance Raja Dance’’ reminds me of the textures of Moroder and Depeche Mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-seven-legacy-of-vijaya-anand&quot;&gt;Chapter Seven: Legacy of Vijaya Anand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anand has composed scores for many films since the 1990s, but few have been as innovative as Dance Raja Dance.
However, his music gave younger music directors the perspective of ``film as a testing ground for popular music.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A.R. Rehman’s early works Roja (1992) and the foundations of urban soundtracks such as Gentleman (1993) are clearly an extension of the experiments of Vijaya Anand and Bappi Lahiri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-8-cultural-impact-and-reappraisal&quot;&gt;Chapter 8: Cultural Impact and Reappraisal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 21st century, ``Dance Raja Dance’’ is being reevaluated through YouTube and Spotify.
The images and music of that time are not “kitsch” but are being reinterpreted as &lt;strong&gt;South Indian Futurism&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For young Kannada-speaking people, this is not just nostalgia, but a starting point for cultural self-expression that moves from the local to the global.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronology-vijaya-anand-and-trends-in-south-indian-music&quot;&gt;Chronology: Vijaya Anand and trends in South Indian music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

timeline
title Vijaya Anand and the history of South Indian film music
1982 : Ilaiyaraaja ushered in a golden age of South Indian music with &apos;Moondram Pirai&apos;
1984 : Vijaya Anand, composer debut
1987 : “Dance Raja Dance” released
1989: Electronic sound became popular in Kannada films, and MTV-style visual production expanded.
1992: International success with A.R. Rehman&apos;s &quot;Roja&quot;
2000 : Re-release of Vijay Anand&apos;s works, remix edition released
2020: “Dance Raja Dance” is rediscovered by young people on YouTube

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background of the times&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mid-1980s: Expansion of youth culture in urban areas of southern India, popularization of television and video, influence of disco/club music&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kannada/Bangalore area: budding IT industry development, accelerating urbanization speed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Film industry: Innovation in production technology and production methods, signs of globalization of music, choreography, and video production&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Music: Introduction of synthesizers/drum machines/electronic sound, increasing number of songs aimed at young people&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-the-beat-blew-from-the-south&quot;&gt;Conclusion: The beat blew from the south&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;code&gt;Dance Raja Dance&apos;&apos; was created in 1987, India had not yet experienced economic liberalization.
However, the&lt;/code&gt;breath of liberation’’ was already resounding within the rhythm of music and dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anand’s achievement lies in the use of music as a harbinger of social change.
His disco beats were not just entertainment, but a declaration for South India to dance its own cultural future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-dance-raja-dance/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-dance-raja-dance/</guid>
        
        <category>Cinema</category>
        
        <category>Disco</category>
        
        <category>Film</category>
        
        <category>80s</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 コルラ・パンディットとエキゾチカの幻影：ポスト戦後アメリカの夢と仮面</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;序章エキゾチカとは何だったのか&quot;&gt;序章：エキゾチカとは何だったのか&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;文：mmr｜テーマ：エキゾチカの創世期におけるコルラ・パンディットの役割と、戦後アメリカ文化におけるオリエンタリズムの美学を探る&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/4d/Korlaorgan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Korla Pandit at the organ&quot; /&gt; 
出典：&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korla_Pandit&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Korla Pandit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1950年代のアメリカ。
テレビが家庭に普及し、冷戦と繁栄が同居する時代、&lt;strong&gt;エキゾチカ（Exotica）&lt;/strong&gt;と呼ばれる音楽が登場した。&lt;br /&gt;
それは、南太平洋・アジア・アフリカなど「異国」を想像上の楽園として描き出す、&lt;strong&gt;オリエンタリズムの音響的表現&lt;/strong&gt;だった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ティキ文化、ハワイアン・バー、ルンバのリズム、そして異国風のメロディ。&lt;br /&gt;
その中心には、&lt;strong&gt;ミステリアスな鍵盤奏者「コルラ・パンディット」&lt;/strong&gt;の姿があった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uChjf1Zmqkw?si=2mU2mDJa1V1Esw63&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px; 
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;目次&quot;&gt;目次&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第1章&quot;&gt;第1章：コルラ・パンディットという謎の男&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第2章&quot;&gt;第2章：戦後アメリカと「異国の夢」&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第3章&quot;&gt;第3章：エキゾチカ音楽の誕生 ― Les BaxterからMartin Dennyへ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第4章&quot;&gt;第4章：テレビ時代の偶像 ― 「Korla Pandit Show」の衝撃&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第5章&quot;&gt;第5章：仮面の裏の真実 ― ジョン・ローランドの告白&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第6章&quot;&gt;第6章：エキゾチカの残響 ― ロンジン・シンフォネットからLo-Fi復興へ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#第7章&quot;&gt;第7章：現代的再評価と文化的転位&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#年表&quot;&gt;年表：Korla Panditとエキゾチカ音楽史（1940–2020）&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#図表&quot;&gt;図表と分析&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#結論&quot;&gt;結論：虚構と真実のあいだで&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第1章&quot;&gt;第1章：コルラ・パンディットという謎の男&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1948年、ロサンゼルスのテレビ局KTLAに現れた「インドの王子」、それが&lt;strong&gt;コルラ・パンディット（Korla Pandit）&lt;/strong&gt;だった。&lt;br /&gt;
ターバンを巻き、深い瞳でカメラを見つめ、ハモンドオルガンを弾く。彼の指は滑らかに鍵盤を踊り、言葉を一切発さなかった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;しかし1990年代後半、ドキュメンタリー映画『Korla』（2014）によって、衝撃的な事実が明らかになる。&lt;br /&gt;
彼の本名は&lt;strong&gt;John Roland Redd&lt;/strong&gt;、アフリカ系アメリカ人だったのだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この「仮面の物語」は、単なる芸名の逸話を超え、&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;戦後アメリカ社会における人種・異国・芸術の三重構造&lt;/strong&gt;を浮かび上がらせる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第2章&quot;&gt;第2章：戦後アメリカと「異国の夢」&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1950年代初頭のアメリカでは、第二次世界大戦の勝利と冷戦の影の中で、&lt;br /&gt;
「未知への憧れ」＝&lt;strong&gt;エキゾチシズム（Exoticism）&lt;/strong&gt;が文化的ブームとなった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ハリウッド映画では『South Pacific』（1958）が大ヒット。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;家庭では「ティキ・バー」が流行し、竹製家具や南国柄のカーテンが庶民の夢を彩った。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;音楽ではラテン、ハワイアン、アラビアン、インド音楽が「幻想的なBGM」として消費された。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この文脈で、パンディットの沈黙と仮面は、&lt;strong&gt;理想化された「異国の静謐」&lt;/strong&gt;を象徴する存在となった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第3章&quot;&gt;第3章：エキゾチカ音楽の誕生 ― Les BaxterからMartin Dennyへ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
timeline
    title エキゾチカ音楽の系譜
    1940 : Les Baxter「Ritual of the Savage」登場
    1957 : Martin Denny「Exotica」ヒット
    1958 : Arthur Lyman「Taboo」
    1961 : Yma Sumac「Legend of the Sun Virgin」
    1990 : Combustible Edisonによる再評価
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les Baxterが1952年に発表したアルバム『Ritual of the Savage』は、&lt;br /&gt;
後のMartin DennyやArthur Lymanのサウンドの基礎を築いた。&lt;br /&gt;
そこでは打楽器、鳥の声、ガムラン、チャイムが交錯し、&lt;strong&gt;「架空の南洋」&lt;/strong&gt;が音響化された。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一方、パンディットはより宗教的・精神的な側面に焦点を当て、&lt;br /&gt;
「瞑想と陶酔のオルガン音楽」という独自の路線を切り開いた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;参照／出典：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Baxter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Les Baxter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Denny&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Martin Denny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第4章&quot;&gt;第4章：テレビ時代の偶像 ― 「Korla Pandit Show」の衝撃&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ul_glviDp2M?si=duNBy74VCRrDdxPI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1951年から放映された「Korla Pandit Show」は、アメリカ初期の音楽テレビ番組の一つだった。&lt;br /&gt;
言葉を発さず、視線と音だけで構築されるその演出は、当時の白人視聴者にとって“安全な異国”を提供した。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;パンディットは&lt;strong&gt;1,000本以上の放送&lt;/strong&gt;を行い、同時期のNat King Coleよりもテレビ露出が多かったという。&lt;br /&gt;
しかし、黒人アーティストとしてのアイデンティティを隠すことでしか成功できなかったという事実は、&lt;br /&gt;
エンターテインメントと人種差別の関係を物語る象徴的な逸話でもある。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第5章&quot;&gt;第5章：仮面の裏の真実 ― ジョン・ローランドの告白&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1998年、『Los Angeles Magazine』が掲載した記事により、&lt;br /&gt;
パンディットの正体が&lt;strong&gt;John Roland Redd&lt;/strong&gt;であることが公となった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;彼は1916年、ミズーリ州セントルイスに生まれ、10代で優れたピアニストとして活動。&lt;br /&gt;
1940年代、ラジオ局で働くなかで「インドの王子」という架空の設定を作り上げた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;それは差別的な時代の中で「黒人音楽家」としてよりも&lt;br /&gt;
「異国の貴族」としてなら受け入れられる――&lt;br /&gt;
という&lt;strong&gt;痛ましい現実への戦略的仮装&lt;/strong&gt;だった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第6章&quot;&gt;第6章：エキゾチカの残響 ― ロンジン・シンフォネットからLo-Fi復興へ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1970年代以降、エキゾチカは一度忘れられる。&lt;br /&gt;
しかし1990年代、&lt;strong&gt;Lounge復興運動&lt;/strong&gt;とともに再評価が始まる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combustible Edison&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Esquivelの再発CD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DJ ShadowやBeckによるサンプリング&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これらの再評価の波は、パンディットにも遅れて光を当てた。&lt;br /&gt;
2000年代以降、彼の映像やレコードはコレクターズアイテムとして再発見される。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;年表&quot;&gt;年表：Korla Panditとエキゾチカ音楽史（1940–2020）&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;年&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;出来事&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1916&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;John Roland Redd（後のKorla Pandit）誕生&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1948&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;テレビ出演開始、KTLAで「Korla Pandit」名義を使用&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1951&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;「Korla Pandit Show」放映開始&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1957&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Martin Denny『Exotica』がチャート1位に&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1960&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;アメリカでエキゾチカブーム最盛期&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1970&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;テレビ出演減少、ラスベガスなどで演奏活動&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;正体が公表される&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;映画『Korla』公開&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;彼の録音が再発・アーカイブ化&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;図表&quot;&gt;図表：エキゾチカ文化の拡散&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph TD
    A[ハリウッド映画] --&amp;gt; B[エキゾチカ音楽]
    B --&amp;gt; C[ティキ文化]
    C --&amp;gt; D[ライフスタイル消費]
    B --&amp;gt; E[現代Lo-Fiサウンド]
    E --&amp;gt; F[チルアウト / Vaporwave]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;結論&quot;&gt;結論：虚構と真実のあいだで&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;コルラ・パンディットの人生は、&lt;strong&gt;芸術的創造と社会的制約&lt;/strong&gt;の交錯点にあった。&lt;br /&gt;
彼の沈黙は、ある意味で最も雄弁な抗議だったのかもしれない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;エキゾチカの音は、単なる“南国風BGM”ではなく、&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;戦後アメリカ人の心の空白を満たす幻想装置&lt;/strong&gt;だった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;その幻想を象徴する仮面の背後に、一人の黒人ピアニストの痛みと夢があったことを、&lt;br /&gt;
私たちは今、ようやく知ることができる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;参照出典&quot;&gt;参照／出典&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korla_Pandit&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Korla Pandit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exotica_(music)&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Exotica (music)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Baxter&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Les Baxter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Denny&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Martin Denny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/column-korla-pandit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/column-korla-pandit/</guid>
        
        <category>Exotica</category>
        
        <category>History</category>
        
        <category>Lounge</category>
        
        <category>70s</category>
        
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 Vijaya Anandと『Dance Raja Dance』 — カーニバルとしての南インド映画音楽</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;序章80年代末南インドが鳴らしたビートの革命&quot;&gt;序章：80年代末、南インドが鳴らしたビートの革命&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;文：mmr｜テーマ：80年代末、インド南部の都市文化がディスコと共に爆発した。Vijaya Anandの『Dance Raja Dance』は、Karnataka州が生んだ音と映像のカーニバルについて&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1980年代後半、インド映画界は変革の渦中にあった。ムンバイのヒンディー映画（ボリウッド）はA.R.レーマン以前の転換期に差し掛かり、サウンドの刷新が求められていた。一方、&lt;strong&gt;カンナダ映画界（サンダルウッド）&lt;/strong&gt;では、&lt;strong&gt;ヴィジャヤ・アーナンド（Vijaya Anand）&lt;/strong&gt;が先駆的な音楽的革新を試みていた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1987年に公開された『Dance Raja Dance』は、単なる娯楽映画ではなかった。それは、&lt;strong&gt;南インド的感性と世界的ディスコ文化の交差点&lt;/strong&gt;であり、地方都市の若者たちにとっての「未来のサウンド」だった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px; 
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第一章vijaya-anandという現象&quot;&gt;第一章：Vijaya Anandという現象&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FC0E48KzEws?si=t5KiwiyVndEMDRAA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anand（本名：S. V. Krishna Reddy）は、1980年代初頭に映画音楽作曲家としてキャリアをスタートさせた。彼は、当時圧倒的な存在だった&lt;strong&gt;Ilaiyaraaja（イライヤラージャ）&lt;/strong&gt;の影響下にありながら、より&lt;strong&gt;都会的・電子的サウンド&lt;/strong&gt;を志向した点で異彩を放った。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;彼の音楽の特徴は以下の3点に要約できる：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;西洋ディスコの導入&lt;/strong&gt; — Giorgio MoroderやVan McCoyのリズム構造を参考にしたシンセベースライン。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;インド伝統音階との融合&lt;/strong&gt; — カルナータカ音楽のラーガを4/4ビートの上に再構築。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;映画的演出との一体化&lt;/strong&gt; — 音楽が単なる挿入歌ではなく、演出の“エンジン”として機能した。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;『Dance Raja Dance』は、これらの要素が最も洗練された形で結晶した作品である。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第二章dance-raja-dance1987という事件&quot;&gt;第二章：『Dance Raja Dance』（1987）という事件&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ecf7DWHrOCw?si=u8czeUUGR57RIcSi&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この映画は、監督D. Rajendra Babu、主演Vishnuvardhan、女優Khushbuという当時のスターが集結した、&lt;strong&gt;ミュージカル・アクション・ロマンス&lt;/strong&gt;の集大成だった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;物語の概要&quot;&gt;物語の概要&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;青年ラージャ（Vishnuvardhan）は、下町のダンサーとして生きるが、テレビのダンスコンテストをきっかけに全国的な人気を獲得する。裏切りや恋、家族の秘密を経て、最終的には「自らのルーツ」を踊りで表現するという感動的な展開を見せる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;このプロットは単純だが、注目すべきはその&lt;strong&gt;演出と音楽の一体化&lt;/strong&gt;である。タイトルソング「Dance Raja Dance」は、インド映画史上初めて&lt;strong&gt;電子ドラムとカンナダ語ラップ&lt;/strong&gt;を組み合わせた曲とされている。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第三章80年代インドにおけるディスコ現象&quot;&gt;第三章：80年代インドにおける「ディスコ」現象&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;『Disco Dancer』（1982, ヒンディー語）や『Ilamai Oonjal Aadukirathu』（1978, タミル語）の成功以降、インド各地で「ダンス＝自由」の象徴としてディスコ文化が普及した。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;南インドではこの流れが独自の変奏を遂げた。ムンバイのディスコが「都会の夢」を描いたのに対し、&lt;strong&gt;カンナダ映画のディスコは“地域の誇り”の発露&lt;/strong&gt;だった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anandの音楽は、エレクトロニクスと民俗打楽器（タヴィル、ドール、ナーダスワラム）を融合させ、農村と都市のリズムを架橋した。&lt;br /&gt;
この「ハイブリッド性」こそが、南インド音楽の核心である。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第四章映像演出とダンスコレオグラフィ&quot;&gt;第四章：映像演出とダンス・コレオグラフィ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;『Dance Raja Dance』のダンスシーンは、当時のインド映像技術の限界を超えるほどの工夫が凝らされていた。照明・スモーク・ミラーエフェクトを駆使し、まるでMTV世代に向けたような&lt;strong&gt;ビデオ・アート的構成&lt;/strong&gt;が展開される。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;振付師は当時新進気鋭だったMugur Sundar（後に著名なダンスマスターPrabhu Devaの父）。&lt;br /&gt;
彼はハリウッド映画のステップを参照しながらも、&lt;strong&gt;バーラタナティヤムの手振り（ムドラ）&lt;/strong&gt;や民俗舞踊の要素を大胆に混ぜ込んだ。&lt;br /&gt;
この「南インド的MTV感覚」は、のちのA.R.レーマンやHarris Jayarajへと継承されていく。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第五章社会背景と観客層の変化&quot;&gt;第五章：社会背景と観客層の変化&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1980年代後半のインド南部は、都市化の波と共に&lt;strong&gt;テレビ文化の拡張期&lt;/strong&gt;を迎えていた。&lt;br /&gt;
国営放送Doordarshanが民放を開放し、地方の若者が「スター」になれる夢を抱いた時代である。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;『Dance Raja Dance』の主人公ラージャがテレビ番組を通じて有名になる設定は、まさに&lt;strong&gt;新自由主義的価値観の萌芽&lt;/strong&gt;を象徴していた。&lt;br /&gt;
労働・階級・家族の呪縛を越え、才能と努力によって成功を掴む——それは「インド版アメリカンドリーム」とも言える。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第六章サウンドトラック解析&quot;&gt;第六章：サウンドトラック解析&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;曲名&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;歌手&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;特徴&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;備考&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dance Raja Dance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;S.P. Balasubrahmanyam&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;電子ドラム＋民俗リズム&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;オープニングテーマ&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prema Prema&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;S. Janaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;シンセ・パッド＋ラーガ調メロディ&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ロマンティックシーン&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ninna Preetige&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mano, Vani Jairam&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;コール＆レスポンス構造&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;コンテスト場面で使用&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finale Medley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Various&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;全曲のリプライズ構成&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ダンス決勝戦シーン&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これらの楽曲は、&lt;strong&gt;FMシンセ（Yamaha DX7）&lt;/strong&gt;や&lt;strong&gt;ローランドTR-707&lt;/strong&gt;など、当時最先端の機材を導入していたことが確認されている。&lt;br /&gt;
特に「Dance Raja Dance」のイントロに聞かれる&lt;strong&gt;ブラスシンセの上昇音&lt;/strong&gt;は、MoroderやDepeche Mode的なテクスチャを思わせる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第七章vijaya-anandの遺産&quot;&gt;第七章：Vijaya Anandの遺産&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anandは1990年代以降も多数の映画音楽を手がけたが、『Dance Raja Dance』ほどの革新性を持つ作品は少ない。&lt;br /&gt;
しかし彼の音楽は、後進の音楽監督たちに「ポピュラー音楽の実験場としての映画」という視座を与えた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A.R.レーマンの初期作品『Roja』（1992）や、『Gentleman』（1993）などの&lt;strong&gt;都市型サウンドトラックの基礎&lt;/strong&gt;は、明らかにVijaya AnandやBappi Lahiriらの実験の延長線上にある。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;第八章文化的インパクトと再評価&quot;&gt;第八章：文化的インパクトと再評価&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21世紀に入り、『Dance Raja Dance』はYouTubeやSpotifyを通じて再評価が進んでいる。&lt;br /&gt;
当時の映像や音楽は「キッチュ」ではなく、&lt;strong&gt;南インド的未来派（Futurism）&lt;/strong&gt;として再解釈されているのだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;カンナダ語圏の若者たちにとって、これは単なる懐古ではなく、&lt;strong&gt;ローカルからグローバルへ向かう文化的自己表現の原点&lt;/strong&gt;となっている。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;年表vijaya-anandと南インド音楽の潮流&quot;&gt;年表：Vijaya Anandと南インド音楽の潮流&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

timeline
    title Vijaya Anandと南インド映画音楽の歩み
    1982 : Ilaiyaraajaが『Moondram Pirai』で南インド音楽の黄金期を築く
    1984 : Vijaya Anand、作曲家デビュー
    1987 : 『Dance Raja Dance』公開
    1989 : カンナダ映画で電子サウンド普及、MTV的映像演出が拡大
    1992 : A.R.レーマン『Roja』で国際的成功
    2000 : Vijay Anand作品の再リリース、リミックス盤登場
    2020 : YouTube上で『Dance Raja Dance』が若者に再発見される

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;時代背景&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1980年代中盤：南インド都市部の若者文化拡大、テレビ・ビデオ普及、ディスコ／クラブ音楽の影響&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;カンナダ州／バンガロール周辺：IT産業発展の萌芽、都市化スピード加速&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;映画産業：制作技術・演出手法の刷新、音楽・振付・映像演出のグローバル化兆候&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;音楽：シンセサイザー／ドラムマシン／電子音響の導入、若年層向け楽曲増加&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;結語ビートは南から吹いた&quot;&gt;結語：ビートは南から吹いた&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;『Dance Raja Dance』が生まれた1987年、インドはまだ経済自由化を迎えていなかった。
だが、音楽とダンスのリズムの中に、すでにその「解放の息吹」が鳴り響いていた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijaya Anandの功績とは、&lt;strong&gt;音楽を社会変動の“予兆”として鳴らしたこと&lt;/strong&gt;にある。
彼のディスコ・ビートは、ただの娯楽ではなく、南インドが自らの文化的未来を踊り出すための宣言だったのだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/column-dance-raja-dance/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/column-dance-raja-dance/</guid>
        
        <category>Cinema</category>
        
        <category>Disco</category>
        
        <category>Film</category>
        
        <category>80s</category>
        
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 山城祥二（大橋力）と芸能山城組 ― 音響・群れ・環境の総合芸術としての探求</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue-where-cyber-and-primitive-intersect---a-person-named-shoji-yamashiro&quot;&gt;Prologue: Where cyber and primitive intersect - A person named Shoji Yamashiro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: mmr｜Theme: About the entertainment Yamashiro-gumi formed in the early 1970s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1970s, there was a person who stood out at the border between Japanese music and visuals.
&lt;strong&gt;Shoji Yamashiro (real name: Riki Ohashi)&lt;/strong&gt;.He graduated from the Department of Agricultural Chemistry, Faculty of Agriculture, Tohoku University, and was interested in life science, information, and sound.With a background of scientific thought and sensibility, he positioned art as ``an experiment to explore the relationship between humans and the environment.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The place for this experiment was Geinoh Yamashirogumi, which was formed in the early 1970s.
More than just a music group, it was a &lt;code&gt;community for comprehensively exploring the relationship between sound, humans, and society&apos;&apos; and was a&lt;/code&gt;place’’ that integrated music, ethnology, information theory, and anthropology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-birth-of-the-entertainment-yamashiro-gumi---art-as-a-group&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: Birth of the entertainment Yamashiro Gumi - Art as a “group”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starting point for the Geino Yamashiro Gumi was the formation of a &lt;code&gt;collective&apos;&apos; of people who came together across universities, companies, and professions.
Doctors, teachers, engineers, students, housewives - people with different professions and philosophies shared an intuitive desire to&lt;/code&gt;live in sound’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning, Yamashiro defined art not as an act of individual expression, but as the expression of a group.
Therefore, their rehearsals were not just performances, but the process of ``sound generating a field.’’
The moment when body, voice, space, and time come together to resonate - that is the starting point for Geino Yamashiro Gumi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Music is the very structure of human consciousness. That’s why the sounds of a group are connected to the sounds of society.”
— Shoji Yamashiro (1982)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-80-types-of-sounds-of-groups-from-around-the-world---quest-for-universal-musical-structure&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: 80 types of “sounds of groups” from around the world - Quest for universal musical structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geino Yamashiro-gumi was active from the late 1970s to the 1980s.
He has actually performed and researched **&lt;code&gt;80 types of ethnic performances from around the world&apos;&apos;**.
This was not just a collection of folk music, but an exploration of the fundamental question,&lt;/code&gt;What is the sound that humans make as a group?’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-examples-of-researchperformance-targets&quot;&gt;◇ Examples of research/performance targets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Music/Rituals&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Research Focus&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bali, Indonesia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kecak, Gamelan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Collective trance and time structure&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;African tropical forest&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pygmy forest singing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Synchronization of environmental sounds and the body&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Eastern Europe Bulgaria&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Female chorus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Unequal meter and overtone structure&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Caucasus Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Male chorus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spatial resonance and sociality&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tibet/Mongolia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Homie chanting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laryngeal resonance and overtone separation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than treating these as “materials,” Yamashiro et al. observed and reconstructed their structure, function, and social significance.
In particular, the &lt;code&gt;acoustic structure that transcends time and space&apos;&apos; of gamelan music in Bali is fundamental to the&lt;/code&gt;group creation’’, &lt;code&gt;information environment&apos;&apos;, and&lt;/code&gt;sound environmental studies’’ of the Geino Yamashiro Gumi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People form groups based on sound. Sound evolves through groups.”
— Shoji Yamashiro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-reaching-akira--fusion-of-electronics-and-ethnicity&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: Reaching “AKIRA” – Fusion of electronics and ethnicity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1988, Geino Yamashiro Gumi composed the music for the world-famous animated film ``AKIRA’’ (directed by Katsuhiro Otomo).
This is where Yamashiro’s acoustic philosophy reaches its peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-acoustic-design-philosophy&quot;&gt;◇ Acoustic design philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bali gamelan polyrhythm × electronic pulse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tibetan esoteric chanting x sampled audio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Urban reverberations and crowd sounds × spatial construction rhythm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not just a theatrical accompaniment, but a ``myth-building through sound’’, an attempt to connect the city and the primitive, the future and memory.
The soundtrack of “AKIRA” has been reevaluated internationally as a fusion of electronic music and ethnic sounds.
It also influenced later world-famous artists such as Aphex Twin, Ryuichi Sakamoto, and Cornelius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-sound-environment---science-and-philosophy-of-listening&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: Sound Environment - Science and Philosophy of “Listening”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;code&gt;AKIRA,&apos;&apos; Yamashiro developed the concept of&lt;/code&gt;environmental studies of sound’’ in parallel with his artistic activities.
He reconsidered sound not just as an auditory stimulus, but as a ``point of contact between information and ecology.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-main-works-and-ideas&quot;&gt;◇ Main works and ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Book title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Publisher/year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Content summary&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Sound and Civilization - Introduction to the Environmental Studies of Sound”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Iwanami Shoten, 2003&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Investigation of the effects of rainforest sounds and gamelan music on the brain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4oOyqoh&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Hypersonic Effect”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Iwanami Shoten, 2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A monumental work that sharply questions the state of health and civilization&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3JADOfD&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Yamashiro defined sound as a &lt;code&gt;communication protocol between humans and the environment.&apos;&apos;
Sound is not a symbol, but an ecological and social activity itself.
This idea resonates with later research on&lt;/code&gt;soundscape’’ and ``media ecology.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sound is an interface between the environment and information.
Music is an algorithm by which a herd synchronizes itself with its environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-sensitivity-as-a-scientist---physiology-of-hearing-and-social-sound&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: Sensitivity as a Scientist - Physiology of Hearing and Social Sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His scientific training at Tohoku University’s Faculty of Agriculture gave Yamashiro a unique analytical perspective.
With an understanding of chemistry, biology, and the environment, he came up with the idea of ​​viewing sound not only as a physical phenomenon, but also as part of life’s activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His approach is a back and forth between scientific observation and artistic practice.
Rather than a laboratory, the human group itself is treated as an “acoustic system.”
There was an ``experimental ethics’’ that sought to match the rhythms of life and society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;``The sounds we hear are images of the world reconstructed in our brains.
So music is the act of rehearsing the very structure of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-crowds-in-the-21st-century---the-significance-of-performing-arts-in-the-information-society&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: Crowds in the 21st Century - The Significance of Performing Arts in the Information Society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the modern age of social media and AI, the concept of “swarm” is becoming important again.
It can be said that the practices of the Geino Yamashiro Gumi anticipated the ``regeneration of communal resonance’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From “individual” to “group”.
From “information” to “resonance”.
The ideals advocated by the Geino Yamashiro Gumi in the 1970s are also the prototype for a ``new community’’ in a network society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music is not something that “communicates”, but something that “resonates with”.
What Shoji Yamashiro explored was performing arts as an ecology of information and emotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronology-the-history-of-shoji-yamashiro-and-the-entertainment-yamashiro-group&quot;&gt;Chronology: The history of Shoji Yamashiro and the entertainment Yamashiro group&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

timeline
title Entertainment Yamashiro Gumi/Shoji Yamashiro Chronology
1946 : Riki Ohashi (Shoji Yamashiro) is born
1969: Graduated from the Department of Agricultural Chemistry, Faculty of Agriculture, Tohoku University
1974: Formed the Geino Yamashiro Gumi and advocated “music as a group”
1976: Announcement of “Environmental Music I-II”
1979: Publication of book “Sounds and Environment”
1983: Integrating world folk music structures with “Ecophony Gaia”
1988: Produced the “AKIRA” soundtrack and received international acclaim.
1996: “Brain and Music Informatics” published
2000: Lectures and presentations on “Environmental Studies of Sound” held in various locations
2020s: Entertainment Yamashiro Gumi’s sound sources are rediscovered and reevaluated overseas

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;official-youtube-channel&quot;&gt;Official Youtube Channel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@Geino Yamashiro Gumi&quot;&gt;Geino Yamashiro Gumi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/CdoGAOuxIGA?si=fFgAYUVdP7U7Ab_G” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-yamashiro-shoji/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-yamashiro-shoji/</guid>
        
        <category>Experimental</category>
        
        <category>Tribal</category>
        
        <category>70s</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 タージ・マハル旅行団と小杉武久 ― 音を解き放つ旅の軌跡</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-starting-point-in-the-1960s-beyond-musical-institutions&quot;&gt;I. Starting point in the 1960s: Beyond musical institutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: mmr｜Theme: A sonic pilgrimage where improvisation and environmental sounds intertwine - A record of a journey to the outside of music, drawn by Takehisa Kosugi and the Taj Mahal Travel Group&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 1960s, Japan’s avant-garde music scene was quietly flourishing.
Centered around the Experimental Workshop and Sogetsu Art Center led by Toru Takemitsu, Kei Ichiyanagi, and Joji Yuasa, the boundaries between genres such as music, dance, video, and lighting were being broken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this period, Takehisa Kosugi was studying violin at Tokyo University of the Arts, but he was beginning to feel the limits of traditional musical forms.He began to see sound as an &lt;code&gt;event&apos;&apos; rather than a&lt;/code&gt;structure,’’ and eventually began to explore improvisation and chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sound begins to live when it is separated from the will of the performer.”
— Takehisa Kosugi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/BdjmQkOOa9A?si=wp3TrXBLiNOIjVPf” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ii-collective-music-and-the-encounter-with-john-cage-1964&quot;&gt;II. “Collective Music” and the encounter with John Cage (1964)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1964, Kosugi formed Collective Music with Toru Takemitsu and Kei Ichiyanagi.
In the same year, he performed with John Cage and David Tudor when the Merce Cunningham Dance Company visited Japan for the first time.
This event marked a decisive turning point in the history of Japanese avant-garde music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas of &lt;code&gt;coincidence&apos;&apos; and&lt;/code&gt;unintentionality’’ presented by Cage had a deep impact on Kosugi.
Rather than having the performer “control” the sound, how do we create a state in which the sound “appears” naturally?
This question became the theme of Kosugi’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iii-the-art-of-resonance-and-action-with-fluxus-19651969&quot;&gt;III. The Art of Resonance and Action with Fluxus (1965–1969)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1960s, Kosugi became close to the international avant-garde movement ``Fluxus’’ and stepped into the realm of performance and happenings.
The act of converting everyday objects into sound sources and dismantling the framework of time and space fundamentally shook the conventional view of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in his masterpieces “Music Expanded #2” and “Catch-Wave”,
Kosugi turned the ``body that performs’’ itself into a piece of work, attempting to record the moment when the sound occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trend had a direct influence on later &lt;code&gt;sound art&apos;&apos;,&lt;/code&gt;environmental music’’, and ``acoustic improvisation’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iv-formation-of-the-taj-mahal-travel-group-19691970&quot;&gt;IV. Formation of the Taj Mahal Travel Group (1969–1970)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1969, Kosugi formed the Taj Mahal Travelers as a new experimental subject.
Seiji Nagai, Takashi Iijima, Masaaki Kikuchi (later left) and others joined the group.
Using violin, cello, electronic equipment, brass, voice, radio waves, etc.
He put into practice the philosophy that ``the place itself becomes an instrument.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;v-traveling-through-sound-from-india-to-europe-19711972&quot;&gt;V. Traveling through sound: From India to Europe (1971–1972)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1971, the Taj Mahal Tour Group departs for a tour of Europe.
Their journey was not just a tour, but a ``sound pilgrimage.’’
Outdoors, with no power source or stage, the performance improvised and resonated with the wind, water, crowd, and radio waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;itinerary-mermaid-map&quot;&gt;Itinerary (Mermaid map)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

flowchart TD
A[&quot;Tokyo, Japan&quot;] --&amp;gt; B[&quot;Delhi, India&quot;]
B --&amp;gt; C[&quot;Taj Mahal, Agra&quot;]
C --&amp;gt; D[&quot;Tehran, Iran&quot;]
D --&amp;gt; E[&quot;Ankara, Turkey&quot;]
E --&amp;gt; F[&quot;Istanbul, Turkey&quot;]
F --&amp;gt; G[&quot;Vienna, Austria&quot;]
G --&amp;gt; H[&quot;Berlin, Germany&quot;]
H --&amp;gt; I[&quot;Amsterdam, Netherlands&quot;]
I --&amp;gt; J[&quot;Copenhagen, Denmark&quot;]
J --&amp;gt; K[&quot;Stockholm, Sweden&quot;]
K --&amp;gt; L[&quot;London, UK&quot;]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This itinerary is an approximate route based on actual records and testimonies.
Improvisational performances in various locations ranged from local cultural facilities, outdoors, to bases for student movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vi-deconstruction-and-expansion-of-sound-the-ritual-of-improvisation&quot;&gt;VI. Deconstruction and expansion of sound: the ritual of improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taj Mahal Tourists’ performances do not have the usual &lt;code&gt;songs&apos;&apos; or&lt;/code&gt;structure.’’
Rather, it is more like the act of emitting sound into the environment and waiting for a chance resonance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use PA systems and microphones creatively,
The entire space was treated as a kind of “resonator.”
Kosugi, the leader, attaches a contact microphone to the violin and manipulates the feedback and radio noise while playing.
We have created an ecosystem in which sound “occurs and disappears.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vii-record-of-taj-mahal-travelers--july-15-1972&quot;&gt;VII. Record of 《Taj Mahal Travelers – July 15, 1972》&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pinnacle of their activities was the album released in 1972.
“Taj Mahal Travelers – July 15, 1972” (CBS/Sony).
This is a live recording of an improvisational performance held around the Taj Mahal in Agra.
It is highly praised as a ``soundscape’’ that perfectly combines time, space, and sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no rhythm or melody on the album.
Instead, the sound of wind, electronic sounds, voices, and the resonance of strings gently intersect,
It presents an experience that invites the listener to go “inside the sound.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;viii-overseas-activities-and-catch-wave-1975&quot;&gt;VIII. Overseas activities and “Catch-Wave” (1975)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After staying in Europe, Kosugi moved to the United States in the mid-1970s.
Develops solo activities that combine electronic acoustics and improvisation.
His 1975 masterpiece “Catch-Wave” (EM Records reissue) is
This is a soundscape piece that makes full use of violin, tape delay, and feedback.
He also influenced Brian Eno and Robert Ashley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ix-activities-and-evaluation-in-later-years&quot;&gt;IX. Activities and evaluation in later years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 1980s, Kosugi has served as music director of the Merce Cunningham Dance Company.
While inheriting the philosophy of John Cage, he deepened the integration of dance and sound.
Until his later years, based on his belief that “sound is a natural phenomenon,” he continued to create expressions that drifted between improvisation, environment, and silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;x-the-legacy-of-takehisa-kosugi-and-the-taj-mahal-tourist-group&quot;&gt;X. The legacy of Takehisa Kosugi and the Taj Mahal Tourist Group&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, their activities include “sound art,” “field recording,” and “ambient music.”
It is being reevaluated as the source of diverse musical trends.
An attitude of listening to sound as a &lt;code&gt;phenomenon&apos;&apos; rather than&lt;/code&gt;material’’ or ``information.’’
This is the most important message that Kosugi left us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronology&quot;&gt;Chronology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Events&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1938&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Born in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1960&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Graduated from the Faculty of Music, Tokyo University of the Arts&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1961–63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Participated in avant-garde experimental music activities with Kei Ichiyanagi, Toru Takemitsu, and others&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1964&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;``Collective Music’’ formed, performed with Cage &amp;amp; Tudor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1965–68&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fluxus-like performances (Sogetsu Art Center, etc.)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1969&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Taj Mahal Travel Group” formed&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1971–72&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Musical pilgrimage from India to Europe&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1972&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;《Taj Mahal Travelers – July 15, 1972》 Announcement&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1975&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Solo work “Catch-Wave” released&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1977–90s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Merce Cunningham Dance Company Music Director&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2018&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Passed away.Passed away at the age of 80.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discography-main-works&quot;&gt;Discography (main works)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taj Mahal Travelers – July 15, 1972&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1972&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4oHy02U&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taj Mahal Travelers – August, 1974&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1974&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4oukW0Y&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Catch-Wave&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1975&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3Js1bYY&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/rPq1FyH1e50?si=WPBJQBi9GGaO5ViE” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion---freedom-of-sound-and-prayer&quot;&gt;Conclusion - freedom of sound and prayer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taj Mahal tour group’s trip was not just a ``band’s overseas performance.’’
It was a spiritual journey that transcended the institution of music and resonated with the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are travelers, not performers.”
― Takehisa Kosugi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even now, half a century later, the sounds they emitted still resonate.
It continues to vibrate quietly in the air, in the memories, and deep in the hearts of the listeners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-taj-mahal-travelers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-taj-mahal-travelers/</guid>
        
        <category>Avant-Garde</category>
        
        <category>Experimental</category>
        
        <category>Art</category>
        
        <category>70s</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 音が育てる焼酎：奄美大島に響く発酵のハーモニー</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue-on-the-island-of-the-sound-of-waves-and-shochu&quot;&gt;Prologue: On the island of the sound of waves and shochu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: mmr｜Theme: An experiment carried out on Amami Oshima to encourage the aging of shochu by making it listen to music.Exploring its scientific basis and cultural background&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amami Oshima, the farthest point of the Nansei Islands.
On this island, brown sugar shochu is surrounded by the sun and sea breeze, and people are quietly ``listening’’ to music.
At night, the faint sounds of classical music, jazz, and island songs flow from the depths of the storage room, and alcohol molecules tremble inside the stainless steel tank.
They say that the sound makes the shochu softer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just a romantic metaphor.The phenomenon that physical vibrations caused by sound waves aids in ripening and brings out the flavor is currently attracting attention.
In this article, we will take a look at the whole picture of the ``acoustically aged shochu’’ that brewers in Amami Oshima are trying to create, from both scientific and cultural perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-the-origin-of-amami-brown-sugar-shochu&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: The origin of Amami brown sugar shochu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amami Oshima’s shochu culture dates back to the late Edo period.
On this island, where sugar cane cultivation was popular, a unique distilled spirit made from molasses from pomace was born - &lt;strong&gt;brown sugar shochu&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1949 (Showa 24), when the Amami Islands were returned to Japan, a special exemption was granted for ``brown sugar shochu’’ as defined by the National Tax Agency.
This is the only shochu standard that allows the combination of brown sugar and rice malt, and has become a cultural heritage exclusive to the Amami Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Brown sugar shochu is made from Amami’s soil, water, and wind.”
—— From an interview with the brewer of Amami Oshima Kaiun Sake Brewery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A soft texture created by the minerality of brown sugar and the soft water of the island.
It wasn’t until the beginning of the 21st century that the idea of ​​using sound to enhance this natural blessing emerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-birth-of-alcohol-that-listens-to-sound&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Birth of alcohol that listens to sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-origin-of-idea&quot;&gt;● Origin of idea&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impetus was the &lt;code&gt;acoustic aging&apos;&apos; of wine that a wine brewer saw in Tokyo.
I learned about an attempt to speed up maturation by playing classical music,
He returned to Amami thinking,&lt;/code&gt;Maybe it could be done with shochu.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, a certain warehouse on Amami Oshima installed acoustic speakers in its storage room for the first time.
The subjects tested were classical music (Bach, Mozart) and island songs (such as Satokuni Taka’s ``Asahabushi’’).
Six months later, the people involved who tasted it were surprised.
“Even though it’s the same raw sake, it was more mellow when I listened to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-mechanism-of-acoustic-maturation&quot;&gt;● Mechanism of acoustic maturation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sound waves cause minute vibrations inside the liquid.
Changing the frequency increases molecular collisions and accelerates the esterification reaction.
This is said to increase the aromatic components and reduce the irritation of alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;``Bass waves move the liquid as deep bass waves, and high frequencies cause the surface layer to vibrate minutely.
It’s like receiving a sonic massage.”
—— Researcher, Faculty of Agriculture, Department of Food Science, Kagoshima University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-sounds-played-by-amamis-storehouses&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: Sounds played by Amami’s storehouses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each brewery in Amami Oshima has a different “style of sound.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Brewery name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Music used&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Effects/features&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sound equipment&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Oshima Kaiun Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Island songs, drums, sanshin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Increased sweetness and richness&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Underwater transducer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Brown Sugar Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jazz (Miles Davis)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alleviates bitterness&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wooden barrel speaker&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Oshima Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Classic (Mozart, Bach)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gorgeous aroma&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ultrasonic vibration plate&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sato no Akebono (Machida Sake Brewery)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Natural sounds (waves, wind, birds)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Soft texture&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Constant temperature storage + built-in speaker&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each brewery has its own unique &lt;code&gt;listening time.&apos;&apos;
Most breweries play the sound at night, but some breweries play the sound throughout the fermentation process.
In particular,&lt;/code&gt;taiko and sanshin’’ are rich in low frequencies and have high transmission efficiency to liquids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-taste-of-sound-seen-through-scientific-eyes&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: “Taste of sound” seen through scientific eyes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experimental data is also being accumulated.
According to a joint study by Kagoshima University,
Shochu that has undergone classical acoustic aging has a higher
&lt;strong&gt;Average 8% reduction in aldehyde content&lt;/strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;Ester ratio increased by 12%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, in sensory tests, the products were highly rated as &lt;code&gt;rich in aroma&apos;&apos; and&lt;/code&gt;not irritating.’’
The increase in molecular movement caused by sound wave stimulation is exactly what creates “taste tuning.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Shochu is alive. When you give it sound, it reacts as if it were breathing.”
—— Chief brewer/Kikaijima Sake Brewery Factory Manager&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-fusion-of-acoustic-maturity-and-shimauta-culture&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: Fusion of acoustic maturity and Shimauta culture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Amami, “sound” is not just background music.
Shimauta is the prayer of ancestors, a dialogue with nature, and the memory of a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song that plays in the storage room is
It is also a labor song for sugarcane farmers who once crossed the ocean.
Although acoustic maturation is a scientific endeavor,
&lt;strong&gt;It is also a ritual to engrave the memory of Amami into shochu&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-the-taste-of-the-future-created-by-sound&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: The taste of the future created by sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, sonic maturity is spreading beyond Amami.
Experiments are progressing with Iki shochu in Nagasaki and barley shochu in Fukuoka.
It has also spread to the world of wine, sake, and whisky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, there may come a time when aging will be controlled by “sound design” generated by AI.
AI composes a shochu aging song,
Alcohol molecules dance to the rhythm——
That day is approaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronology-history-of-amami-shochu-and-acoustic-maturation&quot;&gt;Chronology: History of Amami shochu and acoustic maturation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Years&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Events&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1600s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sugarcane cultivation begins in Amami&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1800s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Production of local shochu using brown sugar as raw material begins&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1949&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Return of the Amami Islands to Japan, special approval for “brown sugar shochu”&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Oshima’s first acoustically aged shochu test begins&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kagoshima University begins scientific research on acoustic maturation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Each brewery develops its own music aging brand&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Acoustic aging becomes popular in sake breweries in Japan and abroad, AI control technology is introduced&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2025&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami brown sugar shochu in preparation for application as UNESCO intangible cultural heritage&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diagram-mechanism-of-acoustic-maturation&quot;&gt;Diagram: Mechanism of acoustic maturation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph TD
A[Sound wave generation from speaker] --&amp;gt; B[Microvibration in liquid]
B --&amp;gt; C [Molecular kinetic activation]
C --&amp;gt; D [Esterification reaction promotion]
D --&amp;gt; E [Increase in aroma components]
E --&amp;gt; F [Taste becomes mellower]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-7-listening-tongue-resonating-heart&quot;&gt;Chapter 7: Listening tongue, resonating heart&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can “hear” sounds through their sense of taste.
For example, it is known that bitterness is perceived to be weaker in a space where soft sounds are played.
In other words, sound and taste are connected in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of listening to the sound of Amami shochu is
It’s not just science, it’s also the reunification of humans and nature.
The sound of the wind, the sound of waves, the sound of singing, and the sound of fermentation.
They become one harmony,
A small universe is playing inside the glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-8-comparison-of-acoustic-experimental-data&quot;&gt;Chapter 8: Comparison of acoustic experimental data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acoustic maturation makes a difference not only in sensory impressions but also in scientific data.
The graph below is visualized based on Kagoshima University joint research (2023) and experimental data from four Amami Oshima breweries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;comparison-of-acoustic-maturation-of-each-brewery-average-value&quot;&gt;Comparison of acoustic maturation of each brewery (average value)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph LR
A[Amami Oshima Kaiun Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;Shimauta/Taiko drum sound] --&amp;gt;|Ester ratio +15%&lt;br /&gt;Aldehyde -10%| B[(Rich aroma, enhanced sweetness)]
C[Amami Brown Sugar Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;Jazz Acoustics] --&amp;gt;|Ester ratio +12%&lt;br /&gt;Bitterness -8%| D[(Mellow, deep flavor)]
E[Machida Sake Brewery (Sato no Akebono)&lt;br /&gt;Natural sound aging] --&amp;gt;|Acidity -5%&lt;br /&gt;Aroma duration +10%| F[(Soft aroma/light)]
G[Amami Oshima Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;Classical Acoustics] --&amp;gt;|Acidity -7%&lt;br /&gt;Alcohol Stimulation -12%| H[(Mellow and rounded taste)]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-of-sound-effects-by-frequency-band-average&quot;&gt;Impact of sound effects by frequency band (average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

pie
title Main effects of each frequency band on acoustic maturation
&quot;Low range (50-150Hz): Promotion of molecular movement/heavy feeling&quot;: 40
&quot;Medium range (300-1000Hz): Oxidation suppression/aroma maintenance&quot;: 30
&quot;Treble range (5kHz or higher): Surface vibration/alcohol stimulation reduction&quot;: 30

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;average-rating-by-music-genre&quot;&gt;Average rating by music genre&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph TD
A[&quot;Shimauta/Taiko 🎵 92 points&quot;] ---|&quot;Taste, aroma, smoothness&quot;| B[&quot;■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■&quot;]
C[&quot;Classic 🎻 89 points&quot;] --- B1[&quot;■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■&quot;]
D[&quot;Jazz 🎷 87 points&quot;] --- B2[&quot;■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■&quot;]
E[&quot;Nature sounds 🌿 85 points&quot;] --- B3[&quot;■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■&quot;]
F[&quot;Silent contrast 🔇 74 points&quot;] --- B4[&quot;■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■&quot;]

style A fill:#f9f,stroke:#333,stroke-width:1px
style C fill:#9cf,stroke:#333,stroke-width:1px
style D fill:#fc9,stroke:#333,stroke-width:1px
style E fill:#bfb,stroke:#333,stroke-width:1px
style F fill:#ccc,stroke:#333,stroke-width:1px

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;*Scores are test results based on the average value of multiple breweries (as of 2023)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-9-amami-brown-sugar-shochu-map-location-of-warehouses-and-acoustic-aging&quot;&gt;Chapter 9: Amami brown sugar shochu map (location of warehouses and acoustic aging)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Amami Islands, there are &lt;strong&gt;10 breweries&lt;/strong&gt; of brown sugar shochu, both large and small.
Among them, &lt;strong&gt;4 breweries have introduced acoustic aging technology&lt;/strong&gt;, and all of them have their own unique “sound” as part of their brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amami-islands-brown-sugar-shochu-map&quot;&gt;Amami Islands brown sugar shochu map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph TD
A[Amami Oshima] --&amp;gt; A1[Amami Oshima Kaiun Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🎶 Shimauta/Taiko drum aging]
A --&amp;gt; A2 [Amami Brown Sugar Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🎷 Jazz Acoustics]
A --&amp;gt; A3 [Machida Sake Brewery (Sato no Akebono)&lt;br /&gt;🌿 Natural sound aging]
A --&amp;gt; A4 [Amami Oshima Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🎻 Classical Sound]

B[Kikaijima] --&amp;gt; B1[Kikaijima Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;⚙️ Under ultrasonic aging test]

C[Tokunoshima] --&amp;gt; C1[Amami Liquor&lt;br /&gt;🥁 Taiko drum sound wave experiment in progress]
C --&amp;gt; C2 [Mashira Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🌾 Traditional fermentation/silence]

D[Okinerabu Island] --&amp;gt; D1[Okinerabu Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🌊 Ocean current aging]

E[Yoron Island] --&amp;gt; E1[Arimura Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🌺 Traditional storage only]
E --&amp;gt; E2[Minanokaze Sake Brewery&lt;br /&gt;🎧 AI sound test introduced from 2024]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geographic-features&quot;&gt;Geographic features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amami Oshima&lt;/strong&gt;: Largest concentration of warehouses.The birthplace of acoustic maturity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kikaijima&lt;/strong&gt;: Features a unique mineral feel made using hard water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tokunoshima/Okinerabujima&lt;/strong&gt;: Research into sea breeze aging and low-temperature fermentation is progressing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yoronjima&lt;/strong&gt;: Culturally, it exists somewhere between Okinawa’s awamori.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-10-diversity-of-flavors-created-by-sounds-and-terrain&quot;&gt;Chapter 10: Diversity of flavors created by sounds and terrain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amami’s topography stretches 160km from north to south, and the humidity, wind direction, and acoustic characteristics of the coastline vary from region to region.
For example, a storehouse facing Tatsugo Bay takes advantage of the sound of waves.
Warehouses located in mountainous areas create a maturing environment that takes advantage of natural reverberations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acoustic maturation is not just a “device”;
&lt;strong&gt;This is the “resonance of the island” where the topography itself becomes an instrument&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Amami is an island like one giant speaker.
The wind plays a low pitch, the waves play a medium pitch, and the voices of insects play a high pitch.”
—— Machida Sake Brewery・Torji talk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-poetry-of-sound-and-fermentation&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Poetry of sound and fermentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I passed in front of the Amami storehouse at night,
A faint sound of sanshin flows from the speakers.
Inside, brown sugar shochu is sleeping quietly.
I’m listening to that melody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and sound slowly refine the taste.
“Maturity of sound” created by Amami’s climate and human wisdom——
It is another kind of music played by the island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommended-brown-sugar-shochu&quot;&gt;Recommended brown sugar shochu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Brewery name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Product name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Capacity/Frequency&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Oshima Kaiun Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brown sugar shochu “Rent”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1800ml/25 degrees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3JaQ5aI&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Oshima Kaiun Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brown sugar shochu “Beni Sango”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;720ml/40 degrees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4qwVYj3&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Machida Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brown sugar shochu “Sato no Akebono (3 years long storage)”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1800ml/25 degrees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4nzD0pp&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Amami Oshima Sake Brewery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brown sugar shochu “Funnel”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1800ml/25 degrees&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/49vtOik&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-shochu-sound-aging/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-shochu-sound-aging/</guid>
        
        <category>Culture</category>
        
        <category>Spirits</category>
        
        <category>Alchohol</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 Salsoul OrchestraとMFSB ― フィラデルフィアからディスコへの進化</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-moment-philadelphia-strings-made-the-world-dance&quot;&gt;The moment Philadelphia strings made the world dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: mmr｜Theme: About the musical revolution that formed the basis of “disco”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 1970s, a musical revolution that later became the prototype for ``disco’’ occurred in Philadelphia, a city on the east coast of the United States.
At the center of this were &lt;strong&gt;MFSB (Mother Father Sister Brother)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They established a new sound called ``orchestra soul’’ by fusing gorgeous arrangements with plenty of strings and horns, a detailed rhythm section, and a soulful spirit.
This lineage later spread to disco culture around the world, and was inherited by house, Latin, and even hip-hop sampling cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-birth-of-the-philadelphia-sound-gamble--huff-and-sigma-sound&quot;&gt;The birth of the Philadelphia Sound: Gamble &amp;amp; Huff and Sigma Sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the 1960s, &lt;strong&gt;Philadelphia International Records (PIR)&lt;/strong&gt;, by &lt;strong&gt;Kenneth Gamble&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Leon Huff&lt;/strong&gt;, supported the Philadelphia music scene.
They began their activities based at &lt;strong&gt;Sigma Sound Studios&lt;/strong&gt;, aiming to replace Motown as a new center for black music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recording was supported by an exclusive session group – &lt;strong&gt;MFSB&lt;/strong&gt;.
The members of MFSB included the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earl Young (drums)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Norman Harris (guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ronnie Baker (bass)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bobby Eli (guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vincent Montana Jr. (vibraphone/arranger)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smooth grooves created by these players became a worldwide brand known as ``TSOP (The Sound of Philadelphia)’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mfsb---the-moment-when-strings-dominate-the-groove&quot;&gt;MFSB - The moment when strings dominate the groove&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1973, the album &lt;code&gt;**Love Is The Message**&apos;&apos; was released under the name MFSB.
The song of the same name became an anthem representing the history of Seoul, and was loved as a&lt;/code&gt;standard bridge song’’ by DJs in the early days of disco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earl Young’s ``four-on-the-floor’’ rhythm was what would later become the basic beat of disco and house.
Furthermore, Vincent Montana Jr.’s vibes and string arrangements gave the rhythms of black music a classical elegance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MFSB was more than just a band, it was the embodiment of a new concept: a ``studio orchestra.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/vYjkjpUor9M?si=6apW0wVkoEBW6BL-“ title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-birth-of-the-salsoul-orchestra-a-declaration-of-independence-for-the-philly-sound&quot;&gt;The Birth of the Salsoul Orchestra: A Declaration of Independence for the Philly Sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1975, &lt;strong&gt;Vincent Montana Jr.&lt;/strong&gt; left MFSB and formed &lt;strong&gt;Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/strong&gt; to pursue his ideals.
Backed by &lt;strong&gt;Salsoul Records&lt;/strong&gt; (founders: Cayre brothers), they aimed for a disco sound with strong Latin elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Montana uses the orchestration skills he cultivated at PIR to fuse Latin percussion and strings.
As a result, a unique equation was created: &lt;strong&gt;Disco+Orchestra+Salsa=Salsoul&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The representative song “&lt;strong&gt;Salsoul Hustle&lt;/strong&gt;” is a perfect symbol of this.
Congas, timbales, strings, horns, and muted guitar all intertwine exquisitely, creating a feel of Latin cheerfulness and Philly sophistication at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/HTJ87N8DkLA?si=CkAZysbSjsJ11h0i” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vincent-montana-jr---craftsman-aesthetics-and-disco-utopia&quot;&gt;Vincent Montana Jr. - Craftsman aesthetics and disco utopia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Montana’s arranging philosophy was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The orchestra is your weapon to dominate the club. Make the vibes, harps, and strings dance in the groove.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His ideal is “music that dances gracefully.”
They gave classical architectural beauty to the dance culture that originated on the street, and elevated the music to an “elegant festival.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, his extreme perfectionism made the studio musicians nervous, and it is said that each recording session required dozens of takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-track-analysis&quot;&gt;Key track analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Song title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Features&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Love Break (Ooh I Love It)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1980&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A treasure trove of sampling.Percussion and horn breaks were overused in later hip-hop.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cited by Public Enemy, Eric B. &amp;amp; Rakim, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Salsoul Hustle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1975&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The origins of early disco.A fusion of 4/4 beat and Latin groove.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Symbolizes a leap forward from the Philly sound.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nice ‘n Naasty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1976&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;String-led dance track.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Features a sophisticated arrangement.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Runaway (feat. Loleatta Holloway)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1977&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A dramatic development featuring female vocals and strings.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reevaluated in later years in the house world.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sampling-culture-and-reassessment&quot;&gt;Sampling culture and reassessment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980s, hip-hop unearthed Salsoul’s legacy.
The horn riff of “Love Break” and the percussion of “Ooh I Love It” were reimagined on Public Enemy’s “It Takes a Nation of Millions to Hold Us Back” and Eric B. &amp;amp; Rakim’s “Paid in Full.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in the 1990s, Masters at Work (Louie Vega &amp;amp; Kenny Dope) reworked Salsoul’s catalog and remixed it in a house context.
Salsoul’s vinyl records have become a club DJ’s holy book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronology-genealogy-from-philadelphia-to-salsoul&quot;&gt;Chronology: Genealogy from Philadelphia to Salsoul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

timeline
title Philadelphia Sound and Salsoul&apos;s Genealogy
1967 : Gamble &amp;amp; Huff establish Philadelphia International Records
1971 : Formed MFSB and started activities with Sigma Sound
1973 : “Love Is The Message” released
1975 : Vincent Montana Jr. leaves and forms Salsoul Orchestra.
1976: The golden age of disco begins with “Nice ‘n Naasty”
1977 : “Runaway” becomes a club hit
1980: “Love Break” released, sampling became standard
1992 : Masters at Work remixes Salsoul Classics
2010s: Re-evaluation and analog reissue boom

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discography-main-works&quot;&gt;Discography (main works)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Artist&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Album&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1973&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MFSB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Love Is The Message&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/48XNk6X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1975&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3X3V4Nt&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1976&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nice ‘n Naasty&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4omnu1p&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1977&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magic Journey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/47txqQN&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1980&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Salsoul Orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Street Sense&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4nBROE7&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-genes-of-orchestral-soul&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Genes of orchestral soul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MFSB and the Salsoul Orchestra are “bridges” in the history of black music.
They made the transition from soul to disco with brilliant and intelligent sound design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blood of Philadelphia certainly flows through the current club culture - house and new disco.
It is the paradoxical beauty of &lt;strong&gt;strings playing the rhythm&lt;/strong&gt;.
The architectural beauty created by Montana’s hands continues to shine deep within the dance floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Sound of Philadelphia never dies—it just keeps dancing.”
― Vincent Montana Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-salsoul/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-salsoul/</guid>
        
        <category>Experimental</category>
        
        <category>Tribal</category>
        
        <category>70s</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 Marvin Gaye：愛と痛みの間で ― ソウルの神が見た救済と破滅</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-motown-star-to-lonely-wanderer-to-tragic-end&quot;&gt;From Motown star to lonely wanderer to tragic end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Text: mmr&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Theme: “Love”, “Social Justice”, and “Inner Darkness”.About Marvin Gaye’s music, a “human anthem” that goes beyond the boundaries of soul music&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hotel room in Brussels, 1982.
Marvin Gaye sat alone at the microphone as the dry beat of a Roland TR-808 blared.
``Midnight Love’’ was an album of prayer born between exile and rebirth, love and self-destruction.
The man who once led the golden age of Motown and spread the word “sexual healing” to the world eventually ended his life at the hands of his father.
The paradox is that those who continued to sing about love were the ones who were the most hungry for love.
Marvin Gaye’s life was the epitome of “the most beautiful, most painful blues” in the history of American music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue-intersection-of-light-and-shadow&quot;&gt;Prologue: Intersection of light and shadow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The life of Marvin Gaye, known as the &lt;code&gt;Prince of Soul&apos;&apos; and&lt;/code&gt;Prince of Motown,’’ was filled with family complications, conflicts with himself, constant creative endeavors, and a tragic ending behind his spectacular success.His music was more than just a “pop hit”; it was an amalgamation of social messages, personal confessions, and grooves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we will reconsider him not just as a musical genius, but as a human being who lived a ``strange life.’‘We will unravel his progress from two axes: changes in music and his own inner oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-early-life-and-early-musical-activities-1939-1960&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: Early life and early musical activities (1939-1960)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;childhood-and-family-background&quot;&gt;Childhood and family background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born Marvin Pentz Gay Jr. on April 2, 1939, in Washington, D.C.Her father, Marvin Gaye Sr., was a church preacher who provided a strict religious education, and her mother, Alberta, was a woman who worked both at home and outside the home.As a child, he grew up singing in the church choir and learning to play the piano and drums.
However, since his childhood, he had been exposed to violence and a controlling attitude from his father, and he was in such a tense state that he later said that he lived with an almighty father who was like a king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approaching-youth-the-us-air-force-and-doo-wop&quot;&gt;Approaching Youth, the U.S. Air Force, and Doo-Wop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1950s, Gaye enlisted in the U.S. Air Force, but was discharged after a short time due to his rebellion against discipline.His interest in music grew, and he began working with doo-wop groups such as “The Marquees” and “The Moonglows.”These activities served as an important foundation for my solo career.
Eventually, he moved to the Detroit/Motown area, and in 1961, he seized the opportunity to make his debut as a solo singer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;encounter-with-motown&quot;&gt;Encounter with Motown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An encounter with Berry Gordy, founder of the Motown label, paved the way for him to become a solo singer.After his debut, while adapting to Motown’s system of mass-producing hits for young people, he began to develop a desire for &lt;code&gt;adult songs&apos;&apos; and&lt;/code&gt;a voice that speaks volumes.’’
During this period, he gradually began to realize that he could move from &lt;code&gt;just singing&apos;&apos; to&lt;/code&gt;talking through songs.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-growth-as-a-hit-maker-1960s&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Growth as a hit maker (1960s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;initial-success-and-struggles-with-the-motown-establishment&quot;&gt;Initial success and struggles with the Motown establishment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1962, he had his first hit with “Stubborn Kind of Fellow.”After that, he released a series of major hits such as “How Sweet It Is (To Be Loved by You)” (1964) and “I Heard It Through the Grapevine” (1968).
At the same time, however, a gap emerged between his desired position as an &lt;code&gt;adult crooner&apos;&apos; and the&lt;/code&gt;youth-oriented R&amp;amp;B hit’’ that Motown wanted, and internal conflict deepened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;duet-era-love-and-sadness&quot;&gt;Duet Era: Love and Sadness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this period, his duet with Tami Terrell was of great significance in his career.Together they achieved success with songs such as “Ain’t Nothing Like the Real Thing” and “You’re All I Need to Get By.”
However, the tragedy of Tami Terrell’s worsening condition, stage collapse, and death had a deep psychological impact on Gay, accelerating the fluctuations in her inner world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-beginnings-of-self-expression&quot;&gt;The beginnings of self-expression&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1968, they had one of the biggest hits in Motown history with “I Heard It Through the Grapevine.”With this opportunity, she began to change from a singer who makes hits to an artist who has something to say.
The experiences of this period form the background that leads to the turning point of “What’s Going On,” which will be covered in the next chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-turning-points--from-whats-going-on-to-here-my-dear-1970-1976&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: Turning Points – From “What’s Going On” to “Here, My Dear” (1970-1976)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-going-on-1971-musical-accusation-and-transformation&quot;&gt;“What’s Going On” (1971): Musical accusation and transformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 21, 1971, the album “What’s Going On” was released.Focusing on social issues such as the Vietnam War, poverty, and environmental destruction, he has established himself as someone who not only sings but also speaks.This was a revolutionary event within the “hit factory” that was Motown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this album, he was involved in writing, composing, and producing the album himself, showing his independence as an artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-get-it-on-1973-and-the-exploration-of-sexuality&quot;&gt;“Let’s Get It On” (1973) and the exploration of sexuality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1973’s “Let’s Get It On,” she delved deeper into the theme of love/desire, demonstrating her “sex appeal” as a soul singer.There is a clear shift from the former “social accusation” to “inner passion.”
During this period, Gaye experienced the joy of creation, as well as the failure of love and financial pressure in his personal life, and these fluctuations cast a shadow on his work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;here-my-dear-1976--establishment-as-a-confessional-album&quot;&gt;“Here, My Dear” (1976) – Establishment as a confessional album&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1976, he released the album Here, My Dear, which reflected the terms of his divorce from his wife, Anna Gordy.Although this was not a commercial success, it was positioned as a “confession album” that was later reevaluated.
After releasing this album, Gaye was exhausted both physically and mentally and reached a turning point in his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-a-period-of-chaos-and-rebirth-1977-1983&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: A period of chaos and rebirth (1977-1983)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tax-avoidance-escape-from-europe-preparation-for-restart&quot;&gt;Tax avoidance, escape from Europe, preparation for restart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1970s and early 1980s, gay men faced many challenges in the United States, including tax problems, drug use, and creative stagnation.Moving to Belgium and spending more time in Europe took on an ``escapism’’ both musically and physically.
In the midst of all this, he was looking for a comeback, seeking new sounds and new environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;midnight-love-1982sexual-healing&quot;&gt;“Midnight Love” (1982)/”Sexual Healing”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 8, 1982, Marvin Gaye released his first album after the transfer, ``Midnight Love,’’ making a huge comeback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major point of this album is the use of the famous Roland TR-808 throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;appearance-and-meaning-of-roland-tr-808&quot;&gt;Appearance and meaning of Roland TR-808&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Roland TR‑808 (commonly known as ``808’’) is an analog/programmable rhythm machine that was introduced in the early 1980s and was not a commercial success at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when it was used in songs such as “Sexual Healing,” the inorganic sound of the drum machine was fused with a modern “soul mood,” and it had a great influence on later soul/R&amp;amp;B/hip-hop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, in “Sexual Healing,” the bass drum, hi-hat, and clap at the beginning are composed of 808-derived sounds, which creates a contrast between the “mechanical groove” and the “human singing voice” throughout the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The production background seems to be that due to production budget and number restrictions at the time, it was necessary to proceed with production using machines rather than using a large band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ``fusion of man and machine’’ also overlaps with Marvin Gaye’s own life - the sound of his own voice (human) and machine (808), and the frustration and rebirth behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;last-live-performance-tv-appearance-and-death&quot;&gt;Last live performance, TV appearance, and death&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1983, he appeared on the TV show “Motown 25: Yesterday, Today, Forever” and performed classic songs from yesteryear.
However, on April 1, 1984, he was shot by his father, Marvin Gaye Sr., at his parents’ home in Los Angeles and passed away at the age of 44.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sudden tragedy symbolized the antinomy of his life: success and despair, salvation and bondage, and left a strong impression not only in the history of music but also as a human drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-legacy-influence-and-the-strange-what-ifs&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: Legacy, influence, and the strange “what ifs”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pioneer-to-the-liberation-of-the-music-industry-and-artists&quot;&gt;Pioneer to the liberation of the music industry and artists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marvin Gaye was not only a hit maker, but also someone who paved the way for artists to independently create music themselves.The album “What’s Going On” was a work in which he was deeply involved in writing, composing, and producing the lyrics, and had a great influence on subsequent R&amp;amp;B/neo-soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the use of the Roland TR-808 on ``Midnight Love’’ also showed new possibilities for the fusion of electronic equipment and soul music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;personal-strange-fate&quot;&gt;Personal strange fate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gay’s life is filled with the &lt;code&gt;curious&apos;&apos; fate of childhood domestic violence, love breakdowns, financial and drug problems, and being shot and killed by his father.This trend goes beyond the framework of a mere&lt;/code&gt;tragic star’’ and reveals a human image of a man whose &lt;code&gt;talent and suffering&apos;&apos; intertwine.
Furthermore, when you think about it from a&lt;/code&gt;what if’’ perspective, there are many hypotheses that come to mind: what if he had broken off his relationship with his father, what if he had not been completely trapped in the Motown system, what if he had continued to live.They are evidence of a ``strange life’’ where chance and necessity intertwine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;re-evaluation-and-expansion-of-expression-in-modern-times&quot;&gt;Re-evaluation and expansion of expression in modern times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after Gaye’s death, his music has been remastered, rediscovered, sampled, and continues to influence new generations today.For example, the discovery of unreleased demo sound sources has also been reported.
In addition, there is a movement to make his life into a film or documentary, and it is gaining recognition not only as a piece of music history but also as a ``human drama.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-chapter-the-soul-that-continues-to-sing&quot;&gt;Final chapter: The soul that continues to sing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on Marvin Gaye’s life, it seems that while music itself was his &lt;code&gt;salvation,&apos;&apos; it was also his&lt;/code&gt;captivity.’‘Through his voice, he continued to sing about the pain of society, the joy of love, and his own struggles.
The words “If you cannot find peace within yourself, you will never find it anywhere else” are attributed to him.
There is a shadow in the light of music, and there is light in the shadow - I think it is this antinomy that makes him more than just a “legend”.
His voice continues to be heard throughout time.
I hope that this manuscript provides an opportunity to reconsider Marvin Gaye, his music, and his strange life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;addendum-chronologycharts&quot;&gt;Addendum: Chronology/Charts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chronology-main-events&quot;&gt;Chronology: Main events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Events&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;April 2, 1939&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Marvin Pentz Gay Jr. is born in Washington, D.C.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Around 1955-56&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Joined the U.S. Air Force and was discharged after a short period of time.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1961&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Debuted as a solo singer.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1964&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hit “How Sweet It Is (To Be Loved by You)” released.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1968&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“I Heard It Through the Grapevine” becomes Motown’s biggest hit.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;May 21, 1971&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Album “What’s Going On” released.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1973&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Album “Let’s Get It On” released.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;November 8, 1982&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Album “Midnight Love” released.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;April 1, 1984&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Shot and killed by his father in Los Angeles.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discography&quot;&gt;Discography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Release year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Album name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1971&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;What’s Going On&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4hzvhGo&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1972&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trouble Man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3WyzzEk&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1973&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let’s Get It On&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4ojSrDq&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1976&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Want You&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/47NalbH&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1976&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here, My Dear&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4olTfaO&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1982&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Midnight Love&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/4ofZkFv&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1981&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Our Lifetime&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/47PNagN&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-marvin-gaye/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-marvin-gaye/</guid>
        
        <category>Soul</category>
        
        <category>60s</category>
        
        <category>70s</category>
        
        <category>80s</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【コラム】 久石譲とスタジオジブリ ― 音楽が紡いだ40年の物語</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue-when-music-moves-the-story&quot;&gt;Prologue: When music moves the story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Text: mmr&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Theme: A long column that looks back on the history of collaboration between Joe Hisaishi and Studio Ghibli, based on facts.Tracing 40 years of musical history, from the origin of the name to the main soundtrack&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the history of Japanese film, the existence of composer Joe Hisaishi (English name: Joe Hisaishi) is unique.
His music is not just ``movie accompaniment’’, but has functioned as an important component that forms the world of the work itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1984’s Nausicaa of the Valley of the Wind, the musical universe created in collaboration with director Hayao Miyazaki has transcended the context of animated films and received international acclaim.
This column carefully traces the relationship between Joe Hisaishi’s musical history and Studio Ghibli works, based on facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;iframe width=”560” height=”315” src=”https://www.youtube.com/embed/faf98cNY8A8?si=ZJ3kmZ7G6yoA6-3m” title=”YouTube video player” frameborder=”0” allow=”accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share”referrerpolicy=”strict-origin-when-cross-origin” allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;

table, td, th {
border: 2px #111 solid;
width: auto;
padding: 10px;
}
th {
background-color: #111;
color: #fff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-early-life-and-musical-foundation&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: Early life and musical foundation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Hisaishi (real name: Mamoru Fujisawa) was born on December 6, 1950 in Nakano City, Nagano Prefecture.
He became familiar with the piano from an early age and studied at the Department of Composition at Tokyo National College of Music.During his student days, he became interested in contemporary music, especially minimal music, and is said to have been influenced by Steve Reich and Philip Glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduating, he worked as a contemporary musician under the name Mamoru Fujisawa, producing many electronic acoustic works and songs for television programs.
From this period, the idea of ​​merging electronic sounds and live music began to emerge, which would lead to the style of later film music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-origin-of-the-name---birth-of-joe-hisaishi&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Origin of the name - Birth of “Joe Hisaishi”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1970s, Mamoru Fujisawa began using his stage name as he expanded his activities into pop music and commercial music.
His name is Joe Hisaishi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has publicly stated that the name was invented in honor of American composer and producer &lt;strong&gt;Quincy Jones&lt;/strong&gt;.
Quincy → It is said to be a play on the Japanese pronunciation &lt;code&gt;kuinshi&apos;&apos; and&lt;/code&gt;hisaishi’’.
Furthermore, “Joe” was taken from the “Joe” of “Jones”, resulting in the English notation “Joe Hisaishi”.
This name was first used officially on the 1981 album Information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;``I wanted to do music that transcends genres like Quincy Jones.
That’s why I chose my name to symbolize “musical freedom.””
― Joe Hisaishi (from NHK “SWITCH Interview”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-nausicaa-of-the-valley-of-the-wind-1984---the-first-encounter-between-film-and-music&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: “Nausicaa of the Valley of the Wind” (1984) - The first encounter between film and music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1984, Hisaishi was chosen to be in charge of the music for the film ``Nausicaa of the Valley of the Wind’’ by Tokuma Shoten and Top Craft.
The song uses a combination of synthesizers and ethnic instruments, which is unusual for animation music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, director Hayao Miyazaki is said to have wanted &lt;code&gt;music that would make you feel the breath between nature and machinery.&apos;&apos;
In response, Hisaishi proposed an&lt;/code&gt;environmental music approach’’ that depicts a worldview through rhythm and tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main theme, “Legend of the Wind,” later became one of Hisaishi’s signature songs.
This success began a long-term collaboration between Miyazaki and Hisaishi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-castle-in-the-sky-1986---establishment-of-the-symphonic-scale&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: “Castle in the Sky” (1986) - Establishment of the symphonic scale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 1986’s Castle in the Sky, Hisaishi turned to a more orchestral sound.
The magnificent theme song ``Kimi wo Seite’’ performed by strings and brass has received high praise both domestically and internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this piece, the melodic simplicity and repetitive structure are cleverly designed.
There is an attempt to integrate the ideas of minimal music into a classical context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Laputa&apos;&apos; can be said to be a work that established the&lt;/code&gt;universality of emotion’’ in Ghibli music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-my-neighbor-totoro-1988-and-memory-of-time&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: “My Neighbor Totoro” (1988) and “Memory of Time”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``My Neighbor Totoro’’ is an example of Hayao Miyazaki’s works in which music is closely tied to the story.
Hisaishi created a warm sound centered around piano, woodwinds, and strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The representative songs “Sanpo” and “Kaze no Torimichi” contain a faint melancholy in the cheerfulness of nursery rhymes.
“Children’s time” is expressed through sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this work, Hisaishi became widely recognized as a ``composer who expresses emotions through sound.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-kikis-delivery-service-1989---growth-and-urban-rhythm&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: “Kiki’s Delivery Service” (1989) - Growth and urban rhythm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiki’s Delivery Service, released in 1989, features a light and airy sound centered on piano and brass.
Since the story is set in a modern European city, Hisaishi introduced elements of jazz and pop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diversity influenced his later works, showing that Hisaishi’s musical idioms were oriented toward ``crossing genre boundaries.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-7-porco-rosso-1992---music-of-romance-and-nostalgia&quot;&gt;Chapter 7: “Porco Rosso” (1992) - Music of romance and nostalgia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Porco Rosso&apos;&apos; adopted a style that was conscious of European music from the 1920s and 1930s.
The main theme,&lt;/code&gt;When the cherries ripen,’’ and the waltz in the play express the emotion and romance of the interwar period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this work, Hisaishi first constructed ``imaginary period music’’ and demonstrated that music functions as part of the period setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-8-princess-mononoke-1997---an-orchestral-exploration-of-spirituality&quot;&gt;Chapter 8: Princess Mononoke (1997) - An orchestral exploration of spirituality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1997, when creating the music for Princess Mononoke, Hisaishi used a full orchestra and chorus to create a sound with religious depth.
The theme of this work is the coexistence of nature and humans, and Hisaishi’s music also develops in a way that supports this idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of a mixed chorus, the profound sound of the timpani, and the placement of silence show the maturity of Hisaishi’s musical diction.
That year, Hisaishi also composed the music for Takeshi Kitano’s ``HANA-BI’’, which received high acclaim in a different context at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-9-spirited-away-2001---establishing-a-worldwide-reputation&quot;&gt;Chapter 9: Spirited Away (2001) - Establishing a worldwide reputation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2001, Studio Ghibli’s Spirited Away was released, and Hisaishi’s music attracted international attention.
The theme song ``Always Again and Again’’ (composed by Joe Hisaishi, sung by Yumi Kimura) won the Best Music Award at the 25th Japan Academy Awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is characterized by the clarity of the melody and the beauty of the “ma”, which enhances the fantasy of the story.
This work won the Academy Award for Best Animated Feature in 2003, and Hisaishi’s name spread around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-10-after-howls-moving-castle-2004---waltz-and-circular-structure&quot;&gt;Chapter 10: After Howl’s Moving Castle (2004) - Waltz and Circular Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004’s &lt;code&gt;Howl&apos;s Moving Castle,&apos;&apos; the main theme&lt;/code&gt;Life’s merry-go-round’’ has a structure that runs through the entire work.
The melody, based on a waltz in triple time, symbolizes the work’s ``circulating time.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his follow-up, Ponyo on the Cliff (2008), he pursued the purity of a nursery rhyme.
The Wind Rises (2013) featured quiet, restrained piano pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout these works, Hisaishi’s music becomes an element that governs the ``inner time of the story.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-11-how-do-you-live-2023---sound-abstraction-and-new-challenges&quot;&gt;Chapter 11: “How do you live?” (2023) - Sound abstraction and new challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you live?, which will be released in 2023, is director Hayao Miyazaki’s first full-length film in 10 years.
Joe Hisaishi was once again in charge of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work uses an abstract sound structure, emphasizing resonance and texture rather than melody.
Hisaishi conducted the London Symphony Orchestra and achieved a high standard of music production in both recording and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is the latest example of Hisaishi’s continued bridging of film music and classical music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronology-list-of-joe-hisaishi-x-studio-ghibli-collaborative-works&quot;&gt;Chronology: List of Joe Hisaishi x Studio Ghibli collaborative works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Director&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Theme song/Representative song&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1984&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nausicaa of the Valley of the Wind&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Legend of the Wind”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;First collaboration&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1986&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Castle in the Sky&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Put You on”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Symphonic composition&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1988&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;My Neighbor Totoro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Walk” and “The Path of the Wind”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Expression of Childhood&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kiki’s Delivery Service&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“City with a Sea View”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Urban Rhythm&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Porco Rosso&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Days of No Return”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nostalgic Waltz&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1997&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Princess Mononoke&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Princess Mononoke”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fusion of chorus and orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Always and Again”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Academy Award Winner&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Howl’s Moving Castle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“The Merry-Go-Round of Life”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Waltz Structure&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ponyo on the Cliff&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Ponyo on the Cliff”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nursery Rhyme Melody&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Wind Rises&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;“Journey”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The tranquil world of music&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2023&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;How do you live? Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;―&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Abstraction of sound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;representative-soundtrack&quot;&gt;Representative soundtrack&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Movie&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;English title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Soundtrack&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nausicaä of the Valley of the Wind*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Original Soundtrack – Toward the Faraway Land&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/48Yc6Uv&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hisaishi and Miyazaki’s first collaboration&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;My Neighbor Totoro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Princess Mononoke&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Princess Mononoke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Original Soundtrack&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3JCbrxI&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fusion of chorus and orchestra&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Original Soundtrack&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/433sD5W&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Received worldwide acclaim&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Howl’s Moving Castle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Howl’s Moving Castle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Original Soundtrack&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/47jIrnv&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A masterpiece in the form of a waltz&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;illustration-joe-hisaishis-musical-structure-mermaid&quot;&gt;Illustration: Joe Hisaishi’s musical structure (Mermaid)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;

graph TD
A[Joe Hisaishi&apos;s musical philosophy] --&amp;gt; B[Minimalism]
A --&amp;gt; C [Memory of melody]
A --&amp;gt; D [Sounding space]
B --&amp;gt; E[Nausicaa of the Valley of the Wind]
C --&amp;gt; F[My Neighbor Totoro]
D --&amp;gt; G[Princess Mononoke]
G --&amp;gt; H[Spirited Away]
H --&amp;gt; I [How do you guys live?]

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-hisaishi-joe/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://monumental-movement.jp/en/column-hisaishi-joe/</guid>
        
        <category>Soundtrack</category>
        
        <category>Anime</category>
        
        <category>Jpop</category>
        
        
        <category>en</category>
        
        <category>Column</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
